{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "A Cheyenne scout killed this man’s ally Looking Glass during a skirmish in the Bears Paw Mountains. This man succeeded his father, Tuekakas, and they shared the same Christian name. This man gave a speech in 1877 during his surrender to General Oliver Howard in which he declared, “I am tired of fighting.\" Howard had followed this man’s tribe for 1,100 miles as they attempted to retreat to Canada from Idaho. For ten points, name this 19th century chief of the Wallowa band of the Nez Perce.",
      "answer": "Chief Joseph the Younger"
    },
    {
      "question": "The archer Tripurantaka and the dog-riding Bhairava are avatars of this deity, the patron of yoga, meditation, and the arts. The Ganges flows from the hair of this rider of the white bull, Nandi. The five mantras of this god reflect the sacredness of that number for this deity, whose sons by Parvati are Kartikeya and Ganesha. Brahma and Vishnu join this blue- throated god to make up the Trimurti. For ten points, name this Hindu destroyer-god who possesses a third eye.",
      "answer": "Shiva or Mahadeva"
    },
    {
      "question": "This conflict coincided with John Doukas’s recapture of Rhodes, Smyrna, and Ephesus. Prior to this conflict, Peter the Hermit led pogroms against Jews in the Rhineland Massacres before rampaging through Hungary. This conflict first came about after Emperor Alexios I Komnenos called for western aid against the Seljuq Turks at the Council of Clermont. For ten points, name this Crusade called by Urban II which established the Kingdom of Jerusalem in the Holy Land.",
      "answer": [
        "First Crusade",
        "Princes' Crusade"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Gerald L. Geison [[GAY-sohn]] showed that this scientist had used deception when reporting his results. This scientist discovered that earthworms could bring diseases to the surface by studying animals dying in \"cursed fields.\" This scientist applied his findings from studying chicken cholera to create the first anthrax vaccine. This scientist dried out infected nerve tissue from rabbits to create the world's first rabies vaccine. For ten points, name this French biologist who names the process of heating milk to kill microorganisms.",
      "answer": "Louis Pasteur 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 8"
    },
    {
      "question": "A presidential candidate from this party continued a speech despite having a bullet lodged inside him after an assassination attempt by John Flammang Schrank. This party, later revived for reformer Robert La Follette’s [[luh-FAH-lets]] 1924 presidential run, first formed after William Howard Taft beat an opponent at the RNC. This party’s first candidate campaigned on Women’s Suffrage and a continuation of his Square Deal program from the early 1900s. For ten points, name this party formed by Theodore Roosevelt to run in the Election of 1912.",
      "answer": [
        "Progressive Party",
        "Bull Moose Party"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In this musical, one of the title characters lends a copy of Uncle Tom’s Cabin to a slave named Tuptim. Based on Margaret Landon's work of historical fiction, in this musical a widow and her son leave India for the promise of a job as a governess and a “brick house.” In one song in this musical, Anna asks the grandson of Rama I, “Shall I Tell You What I Think of You?” For ten points, in what Rodgers and Hammerstein work does Anna teach the wives and children of Mongkut, the ruler of Siam?",
      "answer": "The King and I"
    },
    {
      "question": "Philip II decreed that this substance was essential for Andean natives to consume but should not be used for religious purposes. This crop was targeted by an Andrés Pastrana Arango initiative with Bill Clinton's support in which it was attacked via aerial fumigation. That initiative, Plan Colombia, also attempted to coerce farmers into not producing this raw material which was being processed into a drug by FARC. For ten points, name this plant, the source of a narcotic whose freebase form, \"crack,\" named an \"epidemic\" in the U.S. during the 1980s.",
      "answer": [
        "Coca",
        "Cocaine",
        "Coke"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The Ute [[YOOT]] Pass is directly north of this mountain which inspired Katherine Lee Bates to write the lyrics to “America the Beautiful” after a visit there. This mountain in the Front Range is the easternmost \"Fourteener,\" or mountain above fourteen thousand feet, in the U.S. The namesake of this mountain mapped the course of the Arkansas and Red Rivers during an 1806 expedition. The explorer Zebulon [[ZEB-yoo-lun]] names, for ten points, what “peak” west of Colorado Springs?",
      "answer": "Pike’s Peak 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 8"
    },
    {
      "question": "Until the formation of this government, Eugene Leviné [[yoo-ZHEN leh-vee-NEH]] led a short-lived Soviet Republic in a southern state of this government's country. Polish Marxist Rosa Luxemburg co-led the Spartacus League against this government, leading to her execution by the Freikorps [[FRAI-kohr]]. Hyperinflation caused by this government occurred in part because of their need to pay reparations to the Allies, per the Treaty of Versailles. For ten points, name this German government which collapsed during the rise of Adolf Hitler.",
      "answer": [
        "Weimar Republic or German Reich",
        "Weimar government"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This politician responded abrasively to Jerry Falwell in response to his opposition regarding the appointment of Sandra Day O'Connor. In response to the Packard Commission, this man worked with William Flynt Nichols to create a bill that increased the power of the Chairman of the Joint Chiefs of Staff. Despite being bolstered by Ronald Reagan's \"A Time for Choosing\" speech, this man was soundly defeated in the Election of 1964 by Lyndon B. Johnson. For ten points, name this Arizona politician, credited with laying the foundation for the Conservative Revolution.",
      "answer": "Barry Goldwater 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 8"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "While leading military forces during this conflict, General Raoul Salan attempted a putsch staged from Corsica with support from Governor General Jacques Soustelle. The new Fifth Republic managed to negotiate the Évian Accords, ending this conflict and allowing France to retain the naval base at Mers El Kébir. The end of this war resulted in the mass emigration of Pied-Noirs [[PYAY-NWAHR]] to mainland France. For ten points, name this war between France and the National Liberation Front.",
        "answer": [
          "Algerian War of Independence or Algerian Revolution",
          "or War of 1 November"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This series of attacks by the FLN against targets across French Algeria on the first of November is considered the beginning of the Algerian War and translates into English as \"Red All Saints' Day.\"",
        "answer": "Toussaint Rouge"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The name of this movement may have been coined by critic Clarence Cook. This movement's founder was depicted in the painting Kindred Spirits by Asher Brown Durand. A visit to Northampton, Massachusetts inspired a work by one artist from this movement titled The Oxbow. This movement's founder drew from ancient Roman sculpture for paintings like Destruction in his Course of Empire series. For ten points, name this American art \"school\" founded by Thomas Cole and named for a body of water in eastern New York.",
        "answer": "Hudson River School"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This other Hudson River School artist studied under Thomas Cole, and his paintings Niagara and The Heart of the Andes both drew thousands of viewers to single-work exhibitions in the 1850s.",
        "answer": "Frederic Edwin Church"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man regarded Johnny Torrio as a mentor and William Hale Thompson as a business partner. A Baltimore hospital treated this man's neurosyphilis with one of the first- ever doses of penicillin. The Justice Department convicted this man for tax evasion, leading to his replacement as \"boss\" by Frank Nitti. Seven North Side Gang members died by this man's order in the 1929 Saint Valentine's Day Massacre. For ten points, name this Prohibition-era bootlegger and leader of the Chicago Outfit.",
        "answer": "Al Capone"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Bureau of Prohibition agent, portrayed in film and television as an incorruptible crime fighter, led the so-called \"Untouchables\" in their effort to bring down Al Capone.",
        "answer": "Eliot Ness 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 8"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A novel by this author centers on the intersex Laurence and is titled The Hermaphrodite. This author published the Mother's Day Proclamation as an \"Appeal to womanhood\" following the Civil War. Inspired by a William Steffe song, this person wrote a work which features the chorus \"Glory! Glory! Hallelujah!\" which was written after hearing some soldiers sing \"John Brown's Body.\" For ten points, name this woman who married the founder of the Perkins School for the Blind and composed the \"Battle Hymn of the Republic.\"",
        "answer": "Julia Ward Howe"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The \"Battle Hymn of the Republic\" was a show-stopper at concerts held by this man, whose eighteen number-one hits in the U.S. included \"Heartbreak Hotel\" and \"Suspicious Minds.\"",
        "answer": [
          "Elvis Presley",
          "either underlined portion"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A woman who stalked this man, Princess Catherine Radziwill, wrote a pamphlet defending his character titled The Resurrection of Peter. This man, who orchestrated the Jameson Raid, led the defense of Kimberly during the Second Boer War. A Punch Magazine cartoon depicted this figure as a Colossus with his two feet on Cape Town and Cairo, referencing a railway he hoped to build. For ten points, name this founder of the De Beers Diamond Company who names a scholarship which gives students a full ride to the University of Oxford.",
        "answer": "Cecil John Rhodes"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Under Rhodes, the British South Africa Company defeated Lobengula in the First Matabele War, which took place in what is now this country. Its other ethnic groups include the Shona.",
        "answer": "Republic of Zimbabwe"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 1985, members of this religion carried out the Narita International Airport bombing. After the murder of his father, one leader of this religion began wearing swords representing temporal power and spiritual authority. Members of this religion assassinated Indira Gandhi in retribution for her strike on the Golden Temple in Amritsar, Punjab. Followers of this religion hold that their sacred text, the Adi Granth, is the final guru. For ten points, name this monotheistic Indian religion whose male followers wear turbans.",
        "answer": "Sikhism"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Sikhism was founded by this man, who is also held to be the first Sikh Guru. He noted, \"There is no Hindu, there is no Muslim.\"",
        "answer": "Guru Nanak Dev 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 8"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "After openly testifying about this military event, abolitionist Silas Soule was killed by a fellow militiaman for outing his commander to a Samuel Tappan-led Congressional tribunal. This event was perpetrated by the “Fighting Parson,'' John Chivington, and occurred after he ignored a white flag raised by Southern Cheyenne leader Black Kettle. For ten points, name this 1864 “massacre” of Cheyenne and Arapaho women and children near a namesake Colorado tributary.",
        "answer": [
          "Sand Creek Massacre",
          "Chivington Massacre before mentioned",
          "Battle of Sand Creek"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Texas Mounted Rifles drew with Chivington’s Union forces at the Battle of Glorieta Pass in what is now this U.S. state which entered the Union in 1912.",
        "answer": "New Mexico"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man's last finished novel features William Pitt Ferrars, whose sister is a companion to Adrian Neuchatel, titled Endymion [[en-DIM-ee-on]]. This man ordered Robert Napier to invade Ethiopia. This man also enacted the Public Health Act and introduced competitive exams for Civil Servants. Politically, this man traded power with William Gladstone. A favorite of Queen Victoria, for ten points, who was this Conservative politician, the only Jewish British prime minister?",
        "answer": "Benjamin Disraeli"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Another British politician with a Jewish heritage was this well-known classical economist who was born to Sephardic Jews of Portuguese origin, converted to Unitarianism in 1793, and bought a seat in Parliament for the Irish borough of Portarlington.",
        "answer": "David Ricardo"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Knights of Labor",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Common type of nonviolent protest against businesses involving refusal to purchase products utilized by that organization",
          "answer": "Boycott"
        },
        {
          "question": "1875 act, supported by the earlier Page Act, meant to limit Asian workers supported by the Knights of Labor",
          "answer": "Chinese Exclusion Act"
        },
        {
          "question": "Rival union led by Samuel Gompers",
          "answer": [
            "American Federation of Labor",
            "AFL"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Man who succeeded Uriah Smith Stephens as leader of the organization",
          "answer": "Terence V. Powderly"
        },
        {
          "question": "Late 19th century depression that largely ended the importance of the organization",
          "answer": "Panic of 1893"
        },
        {
          "question": "Railroad tycoon opposed by the organization who attempted to corner the gold market with James Fisk",
          "answer": "Jay Gould"
        },
        {
          "question": "Woman who travelled the country giving her \"Dignity of Labor\" speech as an investigator for the Knights of Labor",
          "answer": "Leonora Barry"
        },
        {
          "question": "1887 massacre of Black sugar cane workers in Louisiana sparked by a Knights of Labor strike",
          "answer": "Thibodaux ] massacre 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 8 Ivan the Terrible"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Regarding Ivan the Terrible, name the...",
      "prompt": "Name the regarding ivan the terrible, name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Empire he led from Moscow",
          "answer": [
            "Russian Empire",
            "Imperial Russia"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Cathedral he had built commemorating the seizure of Kazan and whose architect he legendarily had blinded",
          "answer": [
            "Saint Basil's Cathedral",
            "Cathedral of Vasily the Blessed",
            "Cathedral of the Intercession of the Most Holy Theotokos on the Moat",
            "Pokrovsky Cathedral"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Secret police he created to serve as his bodyguards",
          "answer": [
            "Oprichniki",
            "Oprichnina"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Major city in which that secret police force committed a massacre in 1570",
          "answer": "Novgorod"
        },
        {
          "question": "Period started after the death of his son which ended with the rise of the Romanovs",
          "answer": [
            "Time of Troubles",
            "Smuta"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Ineffectual son who succeeded him, the last Rurikid tsar",
          "answer": [
            "Fyodor I Ivanovich",
            "Feodor the Bellringer"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Former member of Ivan's personal guard who became the first non-Rurikid tsar of his country",
          "answer": "Boris Fyodorovich Godunov"
        },
        {
          "question": "Crimean Khan who was aided in burning Moscow by boyars who were terrified of Ivan's madness",
          "answer": [
            "Devlet I Giray",
            "Giray 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 8 Post-Colonial Philippines"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Regarding the Philippines in the post-colonial era, name the...",
      "prompt": "Name the regarding the philippines in the post-colonial era, name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "President elected in 2016 who has been criticized for his extremely harsh penalties against drug users",
          "answer": "Rodrigo Duterte"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sea it shares with Vietnam and Indonesia that has been the site of territorial disputes with a country that claims everything within a \"nine-dash line\"",
          "answer": "South China Sea"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dictator who was forced to flee to Hawaii after being removed in a 1968 revolution",
          "answer": "Ferdinand Marcos"
        },
        {
          "question": "Politician who opposed that leader and whose assassination at Manilla International Airport led to massive protests",
          "answer": [
            "Benigno Aquino Jr",
            "Ninoy"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Volcano that's 1991 eruption coincided with Typhoon Yunya, leading to hundreds of millions of dollars in damage",
          "answer": "Mount Pinatubo"
        },
        {
          "question": "Second female president who served from 2001 to 2010",
          "answer": [
            "Gloria Macapagal Arroyo",
            "GMA"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Peaceful protest that led to the resignation of Joseph Estrada in 2001",
          "answer": [
            "Second EDSA Revolution",
            "People Power Revolution II",
            "EDSA II",
            "EDSA 2001"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Armed militant group that broke away from the Moro Islamic Liberation Front under the leadership of Ameril Umbra Kato",
          "answer": [
            "Bangsamoro Islamic Freedom Fighters",
            "BIFF 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 8"
          ]
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man forced James Webb of NASA to investigate the existence of the \"Phillips Report\" after the Apollo 1 disaster. In a debate, this man was told by his opponent, \"I will not make age an issue of this campaign.\" Karl Rolvaag appointed this man to fill (20 pts)",
        "Hubert Humphrey's Senate seat while Humphrey was vice president. This man questioned, \"Where's the beef?\" to Gary Hart, and he chose (10 pts)",
        "Geraldine Ferraro as a running mate. Winning only D.C. and his home state of Minnesota, for ten points, who is this presidential candidate who lost to Ronald Reagan in 1984?"
      ],
      "answer": "Walter \"Fritz\" Mondale"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This leader's government outlined seven \"dangerous Western values\" in \"Document Number 9.\" This leader's namesake form of Socialist thought is presented as a continuation of the \"Three Represents\" and Scientific Development Perspective. This leader abolished (20 pts)",
        "term limits, effectively allowing him to rule indefinitely. This leader sought to extend his country's influence in Africa and South-Central Asia through infrastructure investment as part of the (10 pts)",
        "Belt and Road Initiative. For ten points, name this General Secretary of the Chinese Communist Party."
      ],
      "answer": "Xi ] Jinping"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This decade included the Loans for Shares scheme and the Xerox Affair, in which $500,000 was found in a Xerox box. During this decade, the Taman Division's tanks shelled the White House during (20 pts)",
        "Black October. Yegor Gaider led \"shock therapy\" liberalizations in this decade, in which Dzhokhar Dudayev [[JOO-car DOO- dai-yehv]] declared (10 pts)",
        "Chechnya's [[CHETCH-nee-ahs]] Independence before Vladimir Putin crushed the insurrection. Boris Yeltsin was president of Russia in, for ten points, what decade which included the fall of the USSR?"
      ],
      "answer": "1990s"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In his early education at Amasya under the tutoring of Akshamsaddin, this man was influenced to fulfill his Islamic duty. Portugal sent an expedition to fight this man at the request of Sixtus IV, in which 800 men led by Antonio Primaldi were taken to the Hill of Minerva to be executed as martyrs at (20 pts)",
        "Otranto. Besides Italy, this man defeated Skanderbeg in Albania and defeated John Hunyadi after the Peace of Szeged was broken. In (10 pts)",
        "1453, this man ended the Byzantine Empire by conquering Constantinople. For ten points, name this Ottoman Sultan."
      ],
      "answer": "Mehmed II or Mehmed the Conqueror 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 8"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This author depicted a legendary noblewoman who sold her soul to feed her tenants in the verse drama The Countess Cathleen. This author was inspired by a childhood trip to Lough [[LOCK]] Gill to write a poem about wanting to return to a \"small cabin… of clay and wattles made.\" Along with Edward (20 pts)",
        "Martyn and Lady Gregory, this author founded the Abbey Theatre. This poet reflected on a failed uprising against British rule in the poem (10 pts)",
        "\"Easter, 1916.\" For ten points, name this Irish poet, the author of “Sailing to Byzantium” and “The Second Coming.\""
      ],
      "answer": "William Butler Yeats"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This god was traditionally given fifty names that corresponded to an ancient list of kings. Bronze Age depictions of this god show him riding on the mushussu dragon. A notable statue of this god was worshipped in the Esagila temple, from which it was stolen by the (20 pts)",
        "Elamites and Assyrians. This son of Ea is depicted slaying a primordial water deity and retrieving the Tablets of Destiny in the (10 pts)",
        "Enuma Elish. For ten points, name this chief god of the Babylonian pantheon, the slayer of Tiamat."
      ],
      "answer": "Bel Marduk"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Grand Duchess of Baden enlisted this person’s help in setting up medical facilities during the four-month siege of Paris by Prussia, and this person was awarded a Prussian Iron Cross after the Franco-Prussian War. This person innovated the use of corn (20 pts)",
        "husks to act as makeshift bandages during the Battle of Antietam. This person became known as the “Florence (10 pts)",
        "Nightingale of America” during the U.S. Civil War. For ten points, name this founder of the American Red Cross, a nurse known as the “Angel of the Battlefield.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Clara Barton"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The first pope of this name sent a list of sacred books to Exsuperius of Toulouse that was confirmed by the Canon of Trent nearly a thousand years later. A “Savior of Hungary” with this name led the Holy League to save Vienna and was burnt in effigy by the Green Ribbon Club of (20 pts)",
        "London Protestants in the Exclusion Crisis. The third pope of this name launched a crusade against Cathars in southern France as well as one that resulted in the 1204 (10 pts)",
        "Sack of Constantinople. For ten points, give this name of the Pope who called the Albigensian and Fourth Crusades."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Innocent",
        "Innocent I",
        "Innocent III",
        "Innocent XI 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 8"
      ]
    }
  ]
}